Guide to the Franz Sigel Papers 1806-1930 MS 565
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Franz Sigel Papers
1806-1930 (Bulk 1848-1880)
MS 565
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.2 Linear feet (8 boxes, 1 oversize)
Franz Sigel was a German American general during the American Civil War who was enormously popular with German immigrants. His papers include correspondence, including correspondence from President Abraham Lincoln; military materials, which includes battle orders and maps; and other personal writings and ephemera. Many of the materials in this collection are in German. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Sigel, Franz, 1824-1902
Box 1
Box 5
Oversize OS
Box 4
Box 3
Box 2
Box 8
Box 7
Box 6
Provenance
The Franz Sigel Papers were given to New-York Historical Society by Mrs. Robert P.J. Barry in 1946. The oversized maps in Series III, Subseries E were gifted from Franz Sigel III in 1985.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged into seven series which are arranged chronologically.
Franz Sigel Papers
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Legal Documents
Series III: Professional and Political Documents
Series IV: Military Documents
Series V: Writings
Series VI: Clippings, Ephemera, Tributes
Series VII: Family Papers
Biographical Note
November 18, 1824 Sigel born in Sinsheim in the Grand Duchy of Baden (modern day Germany)
1843 Sigel graduated from the Military Academy at Karsruche and joined the army of the Grand Duke of Baden
1848 Sigel joined the Germany revolution and resigned his military commission
May 1852 Sigel moved to New York after being in exile in Switzerland and England
1855 Sigel established the German-American Institute in New York City with his father-in-law, Rudolf Dulon where Sigel taught mathematics, history, and languages
1857 Sigel was hired as a professor at the German-American Institute in St. Louis
1860 Sigel was elected director of St. Louis public schools
May 4, 1861 Sigel was commissioned as a colonel of the 3rd Missouri Infantry
August 7, 1861 Sigel was promoted to brigadier general (effective May 17)
Winter 1861 Sigel resigned from the Union Army in protest when his command was given to Samuel R. Curtis. This is the first of his two resignations.
March 7-8, 1862 Sigel led a division at the Battle of Pea Ridge. This was one of Sigel's few notable military victories during the Civil War.
March 21, 1862 Sigel was promoted to major general of volunteers
Winter 1862-February 1863 Sigel was given command of the XI Corps in the Army of the Potomac, which was mainly made up of German immigrants who wanted to “fight mit Sigel.” Sigel was relieved by Major General Oliver O. Howard in February 1863
February 1864 Sigel was given command of the Department of West Virginia
May 15, 1864 Sigel suffered an embarrassing defeat at the Battle of New Market
July 8, 1864 Sigel was removed from active command
May 4, 1865 Sigel resigned from the Union Army for the second and final time
1869 Sigel ran for New York Secretary of State only to be defeated by the Boss Tweed’s candidate
1886 Sigel was appointed U.S. Pension Agent for New York, a position he held through to 1889
August 21, 1902 Sigel died in New York City
Franz Sigel was born on November 18, 1824 in Sinsheim in the Grand Duchy of Baden, what is now modern day Germany. His military career began upon his graduation in 1843 from the Military Academy at Karsruche when he joined the Grand Duke of Baden’s army. His time in the army was short though, because Sigel resigned his commission in order to partake in the the Revolutions of 1848 in Germany. Sigel was rather notable among the revolutionaries because he had actual military experience. After the Prussians put down the revolution, Forty-Eighters (those who had supported the revolution) fled Germany in droves. Sigel was one of those Forty-Eighters and lived in exile in Switzerland, France, and England.
At some point after the revolution, Sigel married Elsie Dulton with whom he eventually had five children, which included three sons and a daughter: Rudolph, Paul, Franz Jr., and Lulu. No information is available about the fifth child. Sigel's granddaughter, Paul’s daughter, Elsie, was a missionary among Chinese immigrants in New York City. She gained notoriety 1909 when there was extensive newspaper coverage of her sensational murder allegedly committed by one of the immigrants she had been helping.
In May 1852, Sigel, like many Forty-Eighters before him, came to the United States and settled in New York City. Sigel began building his ties with the German immigrant community when he established the German-American Institute in New York City with his father-in-law, Rudolf Duton. Sigel taught mathematics, history, and languages at the Institute. Sigel also taught at the German Turner Society, which was an institution that believed in mixing learning and exercise. During this period Sigel was also active in the 5th New York Militia. Sigel then moved to St. Louis in 1857 to become a professor at the German-American Institute there. In 1860 Sigel was elected director of St. Louis’ public schools.
Like many other Forty-Eighters, Sigel was considered a progressive who opposed slavery. When the American Civil War began on April 12, 1861, Sigel was ready to join the fray. He was commissioned as a colonel of the 3rd Missouri Infantry in the Union Army on May 4, 1861. Soon Sigel became a household name--at least in German households. In what was considered a political maneuver, President Abraham Lincoln promoted Sigel to the rank of brigadier general. The reason for this promotion most likely had something to do with the rallying cry from German immigrants—“I goes to fight mit Sigel.” (There was also a popular civil war song with that slogan for a title.) Sigel was a significant help when it came to recruiting German immigrants for the Union Army. Interestingly, there were several Civil War generals who were German Forty-Eighters including Carl Schurz, Louis Blenker, and Alexander Schimmelfennig.
Unfortunately Sigel’s recruiting successes did not carry over to the battlefield. There were some notable victories during the early years of the war, such as the Battle of Pea Ridge which took place on March 7-8, 1862. However, Sigel’s American military career was punctuated by a resignation in 1861, which he did in protest over being replaced, and numerous losses on the battlefield. Although he was removed from active command, Sigel managed to stay in Lincoln’s good graces due to his popularity with the German immigrants. On May 15, 1864, Sigel suffered an embarrassing loss at the Battle of New Market where the Confederate force had a number of cadets from the Virginia Military Institute whose average age was eighteen. Sigel continued in the Union Army without active command until his second and final resignation on May 4, 1865.
As a civilian, Sigel kept active in politics. He attempted to run for New York Secretary of State in 1869, but he was defeated by Boss Tweed’s candidate. Boss Tweed was a political machine boss. He is associated with Tammany Hall, a notorious New York political machine which was founded in 1876, devoted to Democrats, and fueled by Irish immigrants. In 1886, Sigel was appointed U.S. Pension Agent for New York and he held the position until 1889. On August 21, 1902 Sigel died in New York City.
Sources:
Stephen D. Engle, Yankee Dutchman: The Life of Franz Sigel Louisiana State University Press, 1999.
“Franz Sigel,” Civil War Trust, available at http://www.civilwar.org/education/history/biographies/franz-sigel.html.
“Franz Sigel,” Encyclopedia Virginia, available at http://encyclopediavirginia.org/Sigel_Franz_1824-1902
“Gen. Franz Sigel Dead,” N.Y. Times, Aug. 22, 1902.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Manuscript items written by U.S. Presidents and other notable figures will only be delivered to researchers in a photocopy format. Researchers can also access most presidential papers through their published form. See staff for more details.
Related Archival Materials Note
The New-York Historical Society also holds a number of civil war maps that Sigel collected, available from the Map Collection.
Scope and Content
The Franz Sigel Papers consist mainly of correspondence and military materials. The correspondence, which includes Sigel’s as well as some of his family members, spans over important periods in history, such as the German revolution of 1848, waves of German immigration into the United States, and the American Civil War. The military papers include correspondence, reports, orders of battle, and maps. There are also a number of Sigel’s writings and translations as well as materials that others have written in his honor. Although many of the military documents are in English, most of Sigel's personal documents are in German.
In part because Sigel was a high-ranking military officer during the Civil War whose rise was suspected to be due to political maneuvering than military prowess, there are a number of letters written to President Abraham Lincoln, both from and concerning Sigel. There are also copies of letters and dispatches with Lincoln’s signature. Please note that manuscript items written by U.S. Presidents and other notable figures will only be delivered to researchers in a photocopy format. Researchers can also access most presidential papers through their published form. See staff for more details.
Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Lincoln Correspondence
Box 1/Folder 10: Copy of Lincoln's order to form the Army of the Potomac
Box 1/Folder 12: Copy of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 12: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 12: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 13: Copy of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 14: Copy of dispatch from President's Office
Box 1/Folder 14: Copy of letter to Lincoln from Offciers of the Eleventh Corps
Box 1/Folder 12: Drafts of letter to Lincoln from Officers of the Eleventh Corps
Box1/Folder 14: Copy of letter to Lincoln from Officers of the 3rd Regiment, Ohio Volunteer Infantry
Box 1/Folder 15: Copy of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 15: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 1/Folder 15: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 2/Folder 2: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 2/ Folder 2: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Box 2/ Folder 2: Draft of letter from Sigel to Lincoln
Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894; Burnside, Ambrose Everett, 1824-1881; Butz, Caspar, 1825-1885; Cesnola, Luigi Palma di, 1832-1904; Curtis, Samuel Ryan, 1805-1866; Dulon, Rudolph, 1807-1870; Fremont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Halleck, H.W., (Henry Wager), 1815-1872; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Pope, John, 1822-1892; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906; Sigel Family; Sigel, Elsie Dulon; Stahel, Julius, 1825-1912; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869; Steinwehr, A. von, (Adolph), 1822-1877; Weber, Max, 1824-1901; Windwart, Heinrich; Correspondence; German American Soldiers; German Americans -- Missouri -- St. Louis -- History; German Americans--New York (State)--New York; Germans -- United States; Military maps; Military officers; Military Records; New York (State)--Militia--Muster Rolls; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Participation, German American
- Series I: Correspondence, 1848-1901, undated (Box 2, Box 1, Box 8, Box 3)
  Scope and Content
  Within this series, Sigel’s correspondence is separated into three subseries, based upon the method of organization. There is a subseries of loose correspondence, numbered correspondence, and bound correspondence. The bulk of this correspondence was written during the American Civil War, although it dates back as far as the 1848 revolution and as far forward as 1901, a year before Sigel’s death. There are a number of letters written to President Abraham Lincoln, and a couple with his signature. There does not appear to be a reason why some of this correspondence was numbered, some bound, and others left loose. Many items in this series are written in German.
  - Subseries A: Loose Correspondence, 1848-1901, undated (Box 2, Box 8, Box 3, Box 1)
    This subseries contains correspondence written upon loose pieces of paper. It is organized chronologically and has a number of letters written to Lincoln as well as a few letters with his signature.
    - Correspondence, 1849-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, January-August 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, September 1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, October 1-11, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, October 12-31, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, November 1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, December 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, January-March 1862 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, April-May 1862 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, June 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, July-August 1862 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, September 1862 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, October 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, November-December 1862 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, January 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, February 1863 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, March-July 1863 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, August-December 1863 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, January-March 1864 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, April-December 1864 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1865-1866 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1867-1869 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1870-1871 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1872-1875 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1876-1880 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1881-1886 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1887-1902 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (oversized), 1849-1865 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries B: Numbered Correspondence, 1861-1862 (Box 3)
    The correspondence within this subseries has been numbered, possibly by Sigel as a means of organization. In certain instances, it appears that the numbered progression of correspondence was based on where the correspondence was written. There is a folder within this subseries of numbers that cannot be matched to a particular place or correspondence’s numbered progression.
    - St. Louis Arsenal (1-47), May 16-June 11, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - General 1861 (1-50), May 17-June 28, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General 1861 (51-102), June 24-July 8, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Headquarters Expedition to the South West (1-52), June 28-July 28, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Headquarters, Western Department (1-19), August 15-October 30, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Unmatched Numbers 1861, May 17-September 18, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - General 1862 (1-60), January 5-March 12, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - General 1862 (61-99), March 23-April 3, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Subseries C: Bound Correspondence, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Box 4)
    This subseries contains correspondence that has been bound together, possibly for organizational or storage purposes. Within each bound grouping, the correspondence is organization chronologically.
    - Letters Written and Received (BI), May 8-October 26, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Orders and Instructions Received from Generals Fremont, Hunter, Halleck, and Curtis (EI), August 26, 1861-January 23, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letters Written and Orders Issued by Brigadier General F. Sigel whilst in Command at Rolla (EIII), December 18-24, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Letters Sent and Received, January-August 1862 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Letters Written and Issued, August 27, 1861-March 22, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Brigade Order Book I and Orders of the Department of the West, June 2-July 20, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Brigade Orders II, July 20-August 26, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from General Sigel, June 2-August 27, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters and Orders Received by General Sigel, Missouri, June 3-November 6, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1864 Manifold Writers, June 12-July 7, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series II: Legal Documents, 1849-1889, undated (Box 4, Box 8)
  Within this series are a number of documents both printed and handwritten pertaining to citizenship, the military, and Sigel’s position as New York’s Pension agent. These materials are in both English and German.
  - Legal Documents, 1849-1889 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Legal Documents (oversized), 1857-1861, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series III: Professional and Political Documents, circa 1854-1872 (Box 4, Box 8)
  This series contains materials concerning Sigel’s educational, military, and political endeavors. It contains official documents, handwritten notes, and printed materials. This series is in both English and German.
  - Professional and Political Documents, c. 1854-c.1872 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Professional Documents (oversized), 1858-1870 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Military Documents, 1856-1864, undated (Box 5, Box 8, Box 4, Box 9)
  This series contains materials from Sigel’s American military career, starting from his time in the New York militia through to his service as a general in the Civil War. There are maps, notes, roll books, fliers, reports, receipts, and certificates. This series is in English.
  - Subseries A: New York State Militia Materials, 1856-circa 1858 (Box 4)
    Within these subseries are roll books, rosters, notes, fliers, and other information pertaining to Sigel’s time in the New York militia. This series is in English.
    - New York State Militia, 1856-c.1858 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Subseries B: Maps, Orders of Battle, and Notes, 1861-1864 (Box 4)
    There are maps and other notes concerning military engagements. The maps within this subseries are small in size. This series is in English.
    - Civil War Maps, Orders of Battle, Notes, 1861-1864 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Civil War Maps, Order of Battle, Notes (oversized), 1849-1864 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Civil War Maps, Diagrams, and Notes, Gathered (oversized) 1887, 1861-1887 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Reports, 1861-1862 (Box 5, Box 4)
    This series consists of reports and other documents recapping military excursions that took place during the Civil War. This subseries is in English.
    - 1861 Reports (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Meysenburg Third Volunteer Regiment of Missouri: Enrolling List and Correspondence, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1862 Reports (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Report of the Battle of Pea Ridge, March 6th, 7th, and 8th, 1862, March 1862 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Report of the Battle at Pea Ridge, March 6th, 7th, and 8th, 1862 (copy), March 1862 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1863-1864 Reports (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Report of the Missouri Expedition, Sterling Price, December 28, 1864 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Reports, no date (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Reports (oversized), 1861-1865 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries D: Bills, Receipts, and Certificates, 1861-1864 (Box 5)
    Within this subseries are a variety of bills, receipts, and certificates documenting military life during the Civil War. This subseries is in English.
    - Bills of the Quartermaster, June-September 1861 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Bills, Receipts, and Certificates, 1861-1864 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Subseries E: Oversized Maps, 1862-1878, undated (Oversize OS)
    The oversized maps in this subseries were commissioned specifically by Sigel or document Sigel’s campaign. There are four copies of Map of Route and Positions. These maps are stored in an oversized tube in 2NW Unit 5 A-B Top End.
    - Untitled Map of Headquarters, no date (Oversize OS)
    - Topographical Map of the Battlefield of Bull Run relating to the second day's battle fought on August 30th 1862, no date (Oversize OS)
    - Map of N. Eastern Virginia and Vicinity of Washington, August 1862 (Oversize OS)
    - Map of Route and Positions: First Corps Army of VA Maj. Gen. Sigel Com. from July 7th to Sept. 10th 1862, September 1862 (Oversize OS)
    - Battle Grounds of August 28th, 29th, & 30th 1862 in the Vicinity of Groveton, Prince William, Co., VA, 1878 (Oversize OS)
- Series V: Writings, c.1848-1902, undated (Box 7, Box 8, Box 5, Box 6)
  There are a wide variety of topics in this series. Most of the items are handwritten either by Sigel or others and include letters, poems, stories, notes, diaries, and scrapbooks. The materials are in both English and German.
  - Subseries A: Sigel's Writings, circa 1848-1902, undated (Box 6, Box 5)
    This subseries contains Sigel’s own writings on a variety of topics. There is a mixture of both English and German, with the bulk appearing to be German. Within these materials, there are translations, notes, autobiographical information, and diaries and scrapbooks.
    - Writings, circa 1848-1850 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Writings, circa 1851-1859 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Writings, circa 1861-1869 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Memorandum Books, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Writings, circa 1870-1879 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Writings, circa 1880-1899 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Biographical Dictation, Henry Irving Dodge, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1848-1849 Revolution in Germany, circa 1880-1890 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Autobiographical, circa 1865-1890 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Teaching German in Public Schools, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Civil War, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Poems and Translations, 1855-1901 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Subjects, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Diaries and Scrapbooks: Diary I, 1863-1881 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Diaries and Scrapbooks: Diary II, 1881-1901 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Diaries and Scrapbooks: Notices (partial), 1895-1902 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Scrapbooks and Diaries: Diary VII, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Biographical (oversized), 1880 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Writings, not by Sigel, 1862-1874, undated (Box 7, Box 6)
    This subseries contains a number of poems, mostly handwritten and in German. There are also odes to Sigel’s well known Civil War victory at the Battle of Pea Ridge. There are also a number of letters and other ephemera in a folder of collected works. Some of these items such as the “Citizens and Soldiers’ Health” pamphlet give a glimpse of Civil War life.
    - "The Battle of Pea Ridge", undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Poems, 1862, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Poems, 1874, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Collected Works, 1861-1865, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "Illustrierte Dorstellung Sudewstlichen Feldzug" George G. Freidlein, undated (Box 8, Folder 8a)
    - Map for "Illustrierte Dorstellung Sudewstlichen Feldzug", undated (Box 8, Folder 8b)
- Series VI: Clippings, Ephemera, and Tributes, 1855-1930, undated (Box 8, Box 7)
  Within this series are a number of articles celebrating Sigel, both before and after his death. Several recount his revolutionary history before he came to the United States. There are also many references to what Sigel meant to the German-American community. There are also various pieces of ephemera and envelopes within this series.
  - Clippings and Ephemera, 1855-1899, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and Tributes, 1902-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Original Envelopes and Wrappers, 1861-1864, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Other Envelopes, Wrappers, and Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Clippings (oversized), 1863-1902 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series VII: Sigel Family Papers, 1806-1915, undated (Box 7)